בוקר
טוב, Boker tov, today's דף daf is זיין, zayin, סנהדרין Sanhedrin 7,
but we are behind. So we pick up at the bottom of,
very bottom of ו' עמוד א', vav amud aleph, 6A, and we
are אמר רב אשי, amar Rav Ashi, three, four lines from the
bottom. So we were just going through a whole discussion about פשרה
pshara versus דין, din, compromise versus judgment, and whether you need
three
or one, or maybe even two, but two really was less about
to make the פשרה pshara effective, but to be witnesses. But whether
פשרה pshara is a type of a דין, din, binding arbitration is
a type of a empowering people to render judgment, or whether it's
type of just a contractual agreement, depends on whether you need three
fundamentally or one. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this, אמר
רב אשי שמע מינה פשרה אינה צריכה קניין. amar Rav Ashi shmamna
pshara eina tsricha kinyan. From this debate of three versus one, we
can infer that compromise, פשרה, pshara, binding arbitration, does not need a
קניין, kinyan, does not need somebody to do a קניין סודר, kinyan
sudar, you know, to do the handkerchief thing to say that they're
obligating themselves to the decision. Why? How do you infer that? דאי
סלקא דעתך צריכה קניין, de'isalka da'atach tsricha kinyan, because were you to
say that it would require that, then למאן דאמר צריכה תלתא למה
לי? leman de'amar tsricha tlassa lama li? תסגי בתרי וליקני מיניה. tisgi
bitrei v'likni minei. So what would be the logic of three? Then
if you're doing a קניין, kinyan, then you're actually obligating yourself based
on what the decision would be, and therefore, you know, two should
be enough, you know, two to be עדים. edim. There's a whole
question whether קניין kinyan you need עדים edim or not, you know,
to create a binding obligation through a קניין, kinyan, but you certainly
should not need three, you're just obligating yourself based on what this
person decides. So since there's an opinion that you need three, clearly
we're operating in a mechanism that's not just about imposing an obligation
on yourself, a type of a contractual obligation, because if we were
and you did a קניין kinyan to make that binding, then nobody
would say that three would be necessary. So that seems to be
a, you know, a pretty reasonable point.
But then the גמרא Gemara surprisingly concludes and says the following:
וליקני מיניה. v'likni minei. So why not just, so if it need,
so למה לי תלתא? lama li tlassa? תסגי בתרי וליקני מיניה. tisgi
bitrei v'likni minei. So if it was just, if you did a
קניין, kinyan, who would need three? Just do a קניין kinyan and
you have עדים, edim, right? There should be no need for three.
והלכתא פשרה צריכה קניין. v'hilchesa pshara tsricha kinyan. That actually פשרה pshara
does need קניין, kinyan, presumably, you know, even if you actually require
three,
and or now if, or depending one or three, but the debate
of one or three exists assuming that a קניין kinyan is taking
place. Now it makes sense that you need a קניין kinyan because
you need to make a binding agreement, you know, to say you're
committing yourself to the agreement that's going to come out with, you
know, that the either the panel or the individual will decide. So
it's understandable why you need a קניין kinyan to make it binding,
but then what do you do with the argument of well once
that's true, then who needs three? Then you've just made it binding
whatever somebody says. So if you take a look at
תוספות, Tosfot, תוספות Tosfot says והלכתא פשרה צריכה קניין והא דלא סגי
בתרי משום דהוי כקניין בטעות דלא בקי בפשרה שפיר. v'hilchesa pshara tsricha
kinyan v'ha delo sagi bitrei mishum d'havi k'kinyan b'ta'ut d'lo b'ki b'pshara
shapir. That the reason you would need three would be because at
the end of the day, you know, it's not like you're going
to agree to something that's going to be a roll of the
dice. You know, then you get into like questions about אסמכתא. asmakhta.
You're agreeing to something that is a legitimate compromise
decision, and therefore the argument would be that even though you're saying
you're agreeing to it, if it's any less than three, we would
be concerned that that would actually be a, you know, a non-responsible
decision and a
non-legitimate type of a decision that the panel would arrive at. So
you're, because you're not committing yourself to the arbitrary words that come
out of the mouth of the panel but to a legitimate type
of a פשרה. pshara. Okay, and so that's why you can demand
three even if it has a קניין. kinyan. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara says like this: תנו רבנן כשם שהדין בשלושה כך ביצוע
בשלושה. tanu rabanan k'sheim shehadin b'shlosha kach bitzua b'shlosha. Okay, so this
is the idea that פשרה pshara or ביצוע, bitzua, depending on the
phrase you want, does need three just like דין. din. So it
is a type of a rendering of a decision. נגמר הדין אי
אתה רשאי לבצוע. nigmar hadin i ata rashaiv livtzoa. However, once they
actually the court has, you know, come to the conclusion and we'll
see if you look at רש"י, Rashi, the גמרא Gemara will say
it later, שאמרו איש פלוני אתה זכאי איש פלוני אתה חייב, she'amru
ish ploni ata zakai ish ploni ata chayav, that actually say you're
liable,
you're exempt. That is called גמר דין, gmar din, then you can't
say oh wait, I want to make a compromise. Now why the
other side would agree to a compromise, who even knows, okay, but
clearly once the judgment is rendered you can no longer ask for
compromise. That becomes binding. רבי אליעזר בנו של רבי יוסי הגלילי אומר.
Rabbi Eliezer beno shel Rabbi Yose HaGlili omer. Now we're going to
get into different opinions about whether compromise is a good idea or
not, you know, and it's a sort of a tension between אמת
emet and שלום, shalom, דין... din... might be the most true conclusion
according to the law, maybe even according to justice, but it doesn't
necessarily make all parties
happy, and people could still wind up feeling cheated even if technically
from a legal perspective and feel that it wasn't fair, and a
lot of other things and maybe even justly so. So פשרה peshara
hopefully tries to achieve more of a sense of שלום shalom and
making everybody okay with the final decision, but maybe to some degree
at the cost of אמת. emet. So there's going to be a
question which of these is to be preferred and at some level
the also the issue is sort of at which stage of the
conversation. So let's take a look. רבי אליעזר בנו של רבי יוסי
הגלילי אומר, Rabbi Eliezer beno shel Rabbi Yose HaGlili omer, אסור לבצוע.
assur livtzoa. You, it is forbidden to compromise and come to some
type of binding arbitration. וכל הבוצע הרי זה חוטא, vechol habotzea harei
zeh chotei, and if you do it you're sinning because you're perverting
truth. וכל המברך את הבוצע, vechol hamevarech et habotzea, anybody who gives
a blessing, oh look at them, he managed to work out a
good compromise, הרי זה מנאץ, harei zeh menaetz, you're actually, you know,
you're like you're cursing God, you're blaspheming. ועל זה נאמר בוצע ברך
ניאץ ה', ve'al zeh ne'emar botzea berech ni'etz Hashem, and the בוצע
botzea who blesses, you know, that might mean the one who like
ill-gotten gains is might be the פשט pshat of the פסוק, pasuk,
but here we're reading it that the one who makes a compromise
and who blesses the one who made the compromise is blaspheming God.
אלא יקוב הדין את ההר. ela yikov hadin et hahar. The judgment
has to pierce the mountain no matter how big the obstacle you
have to stay true to the true justice and that can never
be compromised.
Okay, שנאמר, shenemar, the verse says כי המשפט לאלוהים הוא, ki hamishpat
lelohim hu, and that's why you are, it's like you're blaspheming God.
God is entrusting you to instill justice in this world and therefore
you have to be true to the law even if it makes
some people upset. All right, וכן משה היה אומר, vechen Moshe haya
omer, and this is משה Moshe is going to be contrasted to
אהרן. Aharon. אהרן Aharon was, you know, the רודף שלום rodef shalom
and אוהב שלום ohev shalom and so on, and משה Moshe was
very much like the stern justice, you know, coming down from הר
סיני, Har Sinai, God's law. וכן משה היה אומר יקוב הדין את
ההר. vechen Moshe haya omer yikov hadin et hahar. אבל אהרן, Aval
Aharon, באהרן be'Aharon אוהב שלום ורודף שלום, ohev shalom verodef shalom, loved
peace, ran after it, ומשים שלום בין אדם לחברו, umesim shalom bein
adam lechavero, שנאמר, shenemar, then made peace between one person and friend,
תורת אמת היתה בפיהו ועולה לא נמצא בשפתיו, Torat emet hayta be
fihu ve'avla lo nimtza bisfatav, a teaching of truth was on his
mouth and perversion was not found on his lips, בשלום ובמישור הלך
אתי, beshalom uve'mishor halach iti, with peace and with, like,
righteousness the straight path he walked with me, ורבים השיב מעון, verabim
heshiv me'avon, and many he turned away from sin. Now of course
that sounds all very nice, okay, and we know that it's talking
about אהרן Aharon if you see רש"י Rashi because it says the
beginning of the פסוק pasuk is כי שפתי כהן ישמרו דעת ki
siftei kohen yishmeru da'at because, you know, the word, the lips of
a כהן kohen will keep the, you know, knowledge, so teaching. So
anyway but the question is this seems very praiseworthy of אהרן Aharon
but you just said אסור לבצוע. assur livtzoa. So if you look
at רש"י, Rashi, רש"י Rashi says like this, אסור לבצוע, assur livtzoa,
the top second line from רש"י, Rashi, מי שבא לדין אסור לדיינים
לבצוע. mi sheba ledin assur ladayanim livtzoa. Once it's coming to the
judges, once they've presented yourself in a court and they've come to
the place of justice, you have to instill justice. אבל אהרן, Aval
Aharon, what אהרן Aharon did was to make peace before they were
seeking justice. And if you look at the next one, אבל אהרן
אוהב שלום ורודף שלום, Aval Aharon ohev shalom verodef shalom, רש"י Rashi
says וכיון שהיה שומע מחלוקת ביניהם קודם שיבואו לפניו לדין היה רודף
אחריהם ומטיל שלום ביניהם. vecheivan shehaya shome'a machloket beineihem kodem sheyavo'u lefanav
ledin haya rodef achareihem umetil shalom beineihem. Before they would seek justice.
So you always can try to seek peace first, but once you
come to seek justice you can't pervert justice and try to come
up with some type of a compromise. That is the position of
רבי אליעזר בנו של רבי יוסי הגלילי. Rabbi Eliezer beno shel Rabbi
Yose HaGlili.
Okay.
Now, רבי אליעזר אומר, Rabbi Eliezer omer, now that we quoted this
פסוק pasuk about בוצע ברך botzea berech we're going to digress a
little. רבי אליעזר אומר, Rabbi Eliezer omer, הרי שגזל סאה של חטים
וטחנה ואפאה, harei shegazal se'ah shel chitim utachanah ve'afa'ah, somebody stole a,
you know, a pound of flour of grain and he ground it
and he baked it, והפריש ממנה חלה vehiperish mimena challah and separated
חלה, challah, כיצד מברך, keitzad mevarech,
how could this person make a ברכה? bracha? The question of ברכה
bracha on the הפרשת חלה, hafrashat challah, ברכה bracha on המוציא, hamotzi,
debated in the פוסקים, poskim, but anyway, אין זה מברך אלא מנאץ,
ein zeh mevarech ela menaetz, this would not be a blessing, this
would be a blaspheming, it's like מצוה הבאה בעבירה, mitzvah haba'ah be'aveirah,
using the sin and now thinking that you're going to bring it
and bless God over this thing that is stolen. ועל זה נאמר
ובוצע ברך ניאץ ה', ve'al zeh ne'emar uvotzea berech ni'etz Hashem, the
one who breaks the loaf of bread that's how we're reading בוצע
botzea now and gives a blessing is cursing God. רבי מאיר אומר,
Rabbi Meir omer, לא נאמר בוצע אלא כנגד יהודה. lo ne'emar botzea
ela keneged Yehuda. This idea of being a בוצע botzea is said
about יהודה, Yehuda, שנאמר, shenemar, we just had this actually last week's
פרשה, parsha, ויאמר יהודה אל אחיו מה בצע כי נהרוג את אחינו
וכסינו את דמו. vayomer Yehuda el achav mah betza ki naharog et
achinu vechisinu et damo. You know,
what good will it be that we will kill our brother and
cover up his blood? Let's sell him to the ישמעאלים Yishmelim and
they sold him and that brought יוסף Yosef all the way down
to מצרים. Mitzrayim. So somebody said oh, look how great יהודה Yehuda
is, he managed to save יוסף Yosef from the pit. So you
know what רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is saying is, are you kidding?
He was in a position that he could have convinced them to
return... return Joseph to the father. Now I don't know exactly how
we know that, but it's always a question about how do you
respond to half-measures? You say, at least he did something, or do
you say, we're really disappointed, you could have gone the distance. So
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is saying you could have gone the distance.
All right, and if you bless him, then that is blaspheming God.
You need to talk about what he really could have done. וכל
המברך את יהודה הרי זה מנאץ v'chol hamivarech et Yehuda harei zeh
mena'etz and if you bless him you're blaspheming. ועל זה נאמר ובוצע
ברך נאץ השם. ve'al zeh ne'emar uvotzea berech ni'etz Hashem. רבי יהושע
בן קרחה Rabbi Yehoshua ben Korcha אומר מצוה לבצוע. omer mitzvah liftzoa.
Now back to our main point. Okay, rather than saying it's אסור
לבצוע, assur liftzoa, he's saying it's a מצוה, mitzvah, presumably even after
they have come to the בית דין. beit din. So מצוה לבצוע,
mitzvah liftzoa, שנאמר אמת ומשפט שלום
שפטו בשעריכם. shene'emar emet umishpat shalom shiftu beshaareichem. Truth and a judgment
of peace you should judge in your gates. So even when you're
talking to the judges, you should seek out peace, even once it
comes to the judges. והלא במקום שיש משפט אין שלום ובמקום שיש
שלום אין משפט, vehalo bimkom sheyesh mishpat ein shalom uvimkom sheyesh shalom
ein mishpat, says are those two contradictory? If you're seeking out justice,
it's not about finding peace, and it's not about making everybody happy.
If you're trying to make everybody happy, you're not seeking out justice.
אלא איזהו משפט שיש בו שלום הוי אומר זה ביצוע. ela eizehu
mishpat sheyesh bo shalom hevei omer zeh bitzua.
What is the type of a judgment that has peace? That is
compromise. So now it's saying two things. Number one is even when
they come to the judges, they can offer and suggest compromise. But
also it gets back to the question whether this binding arbitration is
a type of a judgment. Is it one or is it three?
It's a type of a judgment that has in it שלום. shalom.
So there is a sense of applying the law, but doing it
with a more flexible approach to context and considerations and all of
that and making a peaceful, you know, a satisfactory, something satisfactory to
all parties, but still a version of justice, of judgment. Okay, not
just a סתם stam compromise. Okay, הוי אומר זה ביצוע. hevei omer
zeh bitzua. וכן בדוד הוא אומר, vechen beDavid hu omer, by
David it says ויהי דוד עשה משפט וצדקה לכל עמו, vayehi David
oseh mishpat utzedakah lechol ammo, till the end of the פסוק. pasuk.
והלא כל מקום שיש משפט אין צדקה, vehalo kol makom sheyesh mishpat
ein tzedakah,
where there's a judgment there's not צדקה, tzedakah, and צדקה tzedakah really
means righteousness, but here it's using צדקה tzedakah in the more rabbinic
sense of, you know, charity, like helping out people that are poor.
Okay, you're the rich guy and really, you know, you have a
right to kick him out of his apartment and this and that
and he'll go penniless, but that would be a משפט mishpat that
has no צדקה. tzedakah. Have a little רחמנות rachmanus on him and
let's find something that actually brings in some other values more than
just strict משפט mishpat judgment, okay? וכל מקום שיש צדקה אין משפט,
vekol makom sheyesh tzedakah ein mishpat, אלא איזהו משפט שיש בו צדקה,
ela eizehu mishpat sheyesh bo tzedakah, what's a type of applying justice
and judgment that still has an element of, like you know, like
God, you want God to be רחמים בדין, rachamim bedin, and has
an element of צדקה tzedakah in it? So הוי אומר זה ביצוע,
hevei omer zeh bitzua, that's ביצוע. bitzua. So now the גמרא Gemara
says אזיל לתנא קמא. azil letanna kamma. Now this actually is going,
that line is actually going to the תנא קמא, tanna kamma, it
seems to work well with the idea that you can suggest ביצוע
bitzua even once it comes to you.
But that works when in the earlier discussion when you're talking about
אמת ומשפט שלום. emet umishpat shalom. Here the צדקה tzedakah is not
the way I was interpreting it. I was trying to get it
to all be consistent and reading the צדקה tzedakah as a type
of a sense of like חסד chesed and kindness that comes in
with your judgment, but the גמרא Gemara here is reading צדקה tzedakah
literally, sticking your hand in your pocket and giving צדקה. tzedakah. So
the way the גמרא Gemara is reading it, that this is actually
going according to the position of אסור לבצוע, assur liftzoa, and that
what David said, what David would do is that David would do
straight justice, no compromise, but then if the poor person suffered as
a result, then David would help, stick his hand in his pocket,
David would give him צדקה tzedakah in order that it should work
out for him as well. So that was his personal funding of
צדקה tzedakah and it was not a, you know, דין din that
had צדקה tzedakah as a piece of it. So again, I would
have rather read that sort of similar to the previous point about
משפט שלום, mishpat shalom, the גמרא Gemara is reading it in line
with the position that it's אסור לבצוע. assur liftzoa. But we get
the idea there are two tracks. One is when they come to
the בית דין beit din all you can do is דין, din,
and the other is no, you can offer them even when they
come to בית דין beit din ביצוע bitzua because that's a type
of a דין ברחמים. din berachamim. Okay,
that would certainly work if ביצוע bitzua requires three. Let's keep on
going. Okay, דן את הדין זיכה את הזכאי וחייב את החייב, dan
et hadin zikah et hazakai vechiyav et hachayav, וראה שנתחייב עני ממון,
vera'ah shenitchayev ani mamon, ושילם לו מתוך ביתו, veshilam lo mitoch beito,
זהו משפט וצדקה. zehu mishpat utzedakah. Okay, so
now the גמרא Gemara is saying explicitly the idea that it is
not just that this last point of משפט וצדקה mishpat utzedakah is
not like דין ברחמים din berachamim but it's sticking your hand in
your pocket. Okay, maybe this is the end of the ברייתא. braita.
If you made the, you know, you gave the ruling and you
said the innocent was innocent and the person liable was liable, and
what wound up is that the poor person now had to be
out, you know, all of his money to the rich person because
technically the rich person was right even though that's like not so
fair, but that is the justice, the judgment. Okay וראה שנתחייב עני
ממון ושילם לו מביתו, Vera she'nitchayev ani mamon v'shilem lo mibeito, then
you the judge, you want a good outcome, not just an outcome
according to law. So you make the עני ani whole by paying
him out of your pocket. זהו משפט וצדקה. zehu mishpat u'tzedaka. That
is both משפט וצדקה. mishpat u'tzedaka. משפט לזה, Mishpat lazeh, it's judgment
for this, you know, for the case itself and for the person
who won, וצדקה לזה, u'tzedaka lazeh, okay, and it's צדקה tzedaka for
the poor person. משפט לזה שהחזיר לו ממונו, Mishpat lazeh she'hechzir lo
mamono, the rich person got his money back and he saw justice
being done, וצדקה לזה ששילם לו מתוך ביתו. v'tzedaka lazeh she'shilem lo
mitoch beito. Okay,
so with that end of the ברייתא, braita, then that is not
a type of רחמים בדין. rachamim badin. That is you do the
judgment and if you want to make it whole, make it whole
out of your pocket. So that is why the גמרא gemara says
that's the approach of that אסור לבצוע. assur livtzowa. Okay, and then
it quotes again the פסוק. pasuk. Now, קשיא ליה לרבי, Kashya leh
l'Rebbi, we'll skip the parentheses. קשיא ליה לרבי, Kashya leh l'Rebbi, האי
לכל עמו לעני מיבעי ליה. Hai l'chol amo l'ani mibayei leh. But
the פסוק pasuk says that דוד Dovid was doing משפט וצדקה לכל
עמו, mishpat u'tzedaka l'chol amo, all his people. But now we're saying
that the צדקה tzedaka part was only for the עניים aniyim who
would lose out, you know, when the judgment went against them.
אלא, Ela, so rather רבי Rebbi says, אף על פי שלא שילם
מתוך ביתו זהו משפט וצדקה. af al pi she'lo shilem mitoch beito
zehu mishpat u'tzedaka. משפט לזה וצדקה לזה. Mishpat lazeh u'tzedaka lazeh. Even
if you didn't pay him, it is judgment and צדקה. tzedaka. What
is the צדקה, tzedaka, even reading צדקה tzedaka not as righteousness but
as like charity? Well, let's see how he reads it. משפט לזה
שהחזיר לו ממונו. Mishpat lazeh she'hechzir lo mamono. It's a
משפט mishpat for the what do you call for the rich person,
he got his money back, וצדקה לזה שהוציא גזילה מתחת ידו, u'tzedaka
lazeh she'hotzi gezeila mitachat yado, and it's a צדקה tzedaka for the
poor person, or not even the poor person, whoever is the liable
party. We no longer have to be rich and poor, that's the
לכל עמו. l'chol amo. But whoever came before דוד, Dovid, it wound
up being משפט mishpat and צדקה. tzedaka. The person who saw justice
being done got his money back and the person who lost in
the judgment, it was also a kindness or a צדקה tzedaka for
that person because what the good that was being done for that
person was that he was no longer holding on to money that
was not his. And by giving the money back, you know, he
was actually doing the right thing and that is a kindness to
him actually, something good you're doing for him that you're helping him
to keep the law and to not hold on to ill-gotten goods.
So I don't exactly get it because the גמרא gemara now is
reading צדקה tzedaka more as like righteousness, which is the פשט pshat
read as opposed to before it was reading it as like charity.
But anyway, but what's pushing the גמרא gemara is the לכל עמו.
l'chol amo. That before the משפט mishpat was only for the person
who won, but the צדקה tzedaka was only in a case if
the poor person was the losing party. And here everybody gets משפט
mishpat and צדקה. tzedaka. Anytime you win you get your justice and
anytime you lose it's still righteousness for you because you're doing the
right thing. Okay, רבי שמעון בן מנסיא אומר שניים שבאו לפניך. Rebbi
Shimon Ben Menasya Omer shnayim she'bau l'fanecha. Okay, but we still have
these basic two approaches about they come to you, are you allowed
to suggest ביצוע bitzua or not? And that has partly are you
perverting דין din or do you see ביצוע bitzua as a type
of דין? din? רבי שמעון בן מנסיא אומר שניים שבאו לפניך לדין
עד שלא תשמע דבריהם. Rebbi Shimon Ben Menasya Omer shnayim she'bau l'fanecha
l'din ad she'lo tishma divreihem. Two people come before you, before you
start hearing, you know, their claims and counterclaims, they just said we
have a suit before you, או משתשמע דבריהם ואי אתה יודע להיכן
דין נוטה, o mishe'tishma divreihem v'ee ata yodea l'hechan din noteh, or
you heard their claims and counterclaims, but it's not obvious to you
yet, you'd have to really get into it before you got a
sense of like who would likely come out, you know,
to win this case. So in that case, אתה רשאי לומר להם
צאו ובצעו. ata rasha'i lomar lahem tze'u u'bitzu.
You can tell them, you know, I would advise you to work
out a compromise. Okay, it's interesting also the different language here. Are
you the one that's being בוצע, botzea, you know, if it's a
type of a judgment, maybe you are, maybe it's a type of
a דין ברחמים din berachamim and you the court is going to
operate in your binding arbitration mode, in your ביצוע bitzua mode. Or
are you offering to them this alternative? And he sort of seems
to say like as that. Then you can sort of, you know,
suggest that they go and work out on their own some compromise.
צאו ובצעו. Tze'u u'bitzu. משתשמע דבריהם ואי אתה יודע להיכן דין נוטה,
Mishe'tishma divreihem v'ee ata yodea l'hechan din noteh,
once you've heard their claims and counterclaims and you have a sense
who's the who's the right party here, in that case אי אתה
רשאי לומר להם צאו ובצעו. ee ata rasha'i lomar lahem tze'u u'bitzu.
In that case, you cannot recommend that they go to work out
some compromise. Why is that? So the גמרא gemara quotes a פסוק,
pasuk, שנאמר, she'ne'emar, as it says, פוטר מים ראשית מדון. Potair mayim
reshit madon. If you want to, the way רש"י Rashi reads this,
exempt yourself from water, from the from the debate, from the judgment,
then you can do it ראשית מדון reshit madon at the beginning
of the contention before you've heard their word, או לפני התגלה הריב.
o v'lifnei hitgala hariv. Before the debate, the argument has become exposed
and revealed, נטוש nitosh
then you can abandon it. קודם שנתגלה הריב אתה יכול לנטושו Kodem
shenitgala hariv atah yachol lintosho but before it's been revealed you can
abandon it. משנתגלה הריב mishenitgala hariv after it's become revealed אי אתה
יכול לנטושו i atah yachol lintosho you cannot abandon it. Okay, so
this seems to be a sense not that this is, I mean
you could work obviously this in with the idea that ביצוע bitzuah
is a type of רחמים בדין, rachamim bedin, but the idea that
it says that you're telling them you guys go out and compromise
and the word about your נטוש nitosh your abandoning does not seem
like you are bringing a different type of justice to this, but
you're exempting yourself from it. You're walking away. You guys figure it
out. And you are not able to walk away once
judgment is already being activated here because you already are seeing where
the judgment lies. That requires you then to see that through. Okay,
so what we really have here is three opinions. One is
the parties come to you, that means that they're in a court
of justice, they're asking for justice, you're responsible to administer justice. That
was the first opinion. The other is even after they've come to
you, not exactly clear at what stage, who knows, maybe even after
you have a sense which way it is going, you can offer
that you maybe specifically should do this type of a אמת ומשפט
שלום emet umishpat shalom because maybe it's a type of a רחמים
בדין, rachamim bedin, it's a certain type of justice, ביצוע. bitzuah. Okay,
but that's the one that you can sort of always maybe or
certainly at a very late stage suggest it. And the other sort
of sees this would yet is more in line with the first
one, yes, you would be abandoning your responsibility of administering justice, but
it's not as soon as they walk in, it's only when it's
clear which way the judgment is leaning. All right, so now the
גמרא Gemara continues like this. ריש
לקיש
Reish
Lakish
or some have רבי יהושע בן לקיש, Rabbi Yehoshua ben Lakish, different
גירסא girsa says אמר שניים שבאו לדין amar shnayim sheba'u ledin two
people came to judgment. אחד רך
ואחד קשה echad rach ve'echad kasheh one is very soft and the
other is very
firm, different personalities
and we're going to have to figure out how that's going to
play out in the court. So עד שלא תשמע דבריהן או משתשמע
דבריהן ואי אתה יודע להיכן הדין נוטה אתה רשאי לומר להם איני
נזקק לכם. ad shelo tishma divreihen o mishetishma divreihen ve'i atah yode'a
leheichan hadin noteh atah rashai lomar lahem eini nizkak lachem. So you're
concerned about what's going to be because based on how you're going
to judge and is the firm guy going to come after you
and so on. This really gets to difficult issues because the judge
says לא תגורו מפני איש lo taguru mipnei ish don't be afraid
of people,
but judges are human. So is there a way that you could
recuse yourself from a case rather than if you are concerned that
you won't be able to deal with the בעלי דין ba'alei din
that are coming and the way they will attack you and so
on? So what ריש לקיש Reish Lakish says or רבי יהושע בן
לקיש Rabbi Yehoshua ben Lakish says is before you actually have engaged
them
or משתשמע דבריהן ואי אתה יודע להיכן הדין נוטה mishetishma divreihen ve'i
atah yode'a leheichan hadin noteh or same type of an idea before
you know which way the judgment is going, in that case אתה
רשאי לומר להם איני נזקק לכם. atah rashai lomar lahem eini nizkak
lachem. You are able to say look I'm going to recuse myself.
Okay, same idea that this is a form of stepping away. So
before it was פשרה peshara was a form of stepping away, here
it's just total stepping away because you don't want to get in
trouble. And until you have a sense where it's going you are
not yet considered to be compromising your integrity, perverting justice, and you're
allowed to step away. איני נזקק לכם שמא יתחייב חזק ונמצא חזק
רודפו eini nizkak lachem shema yitchayev chazak venimtza chazak rodfo because you're
afraid that the one who is the firm guy is going to
be found guilty and he's going to come and chase after you.
משתשמע דבריהן ואתה יודע להיכן הדין נוטה mishetishma divreihen ve'atah yode'a leheichan
hadin noteh but once you have a sense which way the judgment
is going, then that locks you in. Now you are responsible to
see it through. You cannot step away now, that would be a
perversion of your obligation of justice. אי אתה רשאי לומר להם איני
נזקק לכם i atah rashai lomar lahem eini nizkak lachem at that
stage you cannot say I'm no longer dealing with this. שנאמר shene'emar
and this is exactly what the פסוק Pasuk is about, לא תגורו
מפני איש כי המשפט לאלוהים הוא. lo taguru mipnei ish ki hamishpat
le'lokim hu. Do not be afraid of any man,
you're doing God's justice. So actually it's clear that a פסוק Pasuk
says you can't step away and you can't be afraid. The חידוש
chiddush here is it allows you to step away at earlier stages.
רבי יהושע בן קרחה Rabbi Yehoshua ben Korcha says מניין לתלמיד שיושב
לפני רבו וראה זכות לעני וחובה לעשיר מניין שלא ישתוק. minayin letalmid
sheyoshev lifnei rabo vera'ah zechut le'ani vechovah le'ashir minayin shelo yishtok.
How do you know if somebody is there and they're like a
clerk, they're sitting in front of their Rebbe but they're listening to
the court case and they see that
there's merit for the poor person, something could be argued in his
defense or something bad for the rich person? It really could go
the other way too, but he sees something
that he needs to speak up, he wants justice to be done.
מניין שלא ישתוק minayin shelo yishtok how do you know that he
cannot be silent? שנאמר לא תגורו מפני איש shene'emar lo taguru mipnei
ish do not be afraid of any person. But here תגורו taguru
is read as As like אגור agur to gather in your words,
you know, you have a responsibility to share them and not be
afraid. So don't be afraid of your רבי Rebbe and don't even
be afraid of the rich person. I mean, that's presumably why it
was framed that way. You have a responsibility to justice and to
speak up. רבי חנינא אומר Rabbi Chanina omer לא תכניס דבריך מפני
איש. lo tachnis devarecha mipnei ish. This is presumably the point. Don't
hold your word back because of somebody even if you're not the
judge and you're just sitting there and observing the case. So that
creates an even greater responsibility. I mean, more greater in the sense
of more than we would have imagined in terms of who's responsible.
והיו העדים יודעים את מי הם מעידים ולפני מי הם מעידים ומי
עתיד ליפרע מהם. V'hayu ha'edim yodim et mi hem mei'idim v'lifnei mi
hem mei'idim umi atid lipara mehem. And now a slightly different point.
The witnesses should be aware of who are they judging and before
who they're testifying and who is going to, you know, exact from
them. So before whom is God, who's going to exact from them
is God. But now we're going to find out even את מי
הם מעידים, et mi hem mei'idim, who are they testifying against, to
some degree is also God, right? So now the same way you
have all this heavy responsibility on the judges to see through the
truth, heavy responsibility on the witnesses. Okay. שנאמר Shenemar as the פסוק
pasuk says, ועמדו שני האנשים אשר להם הריב לפני השם, v'amdu shnei
ha'anashim asher lahem hariv lifnei Hashem, the two people that have the
judgment and this is read to not be referring to the litigants
but for the עדים edim who should stand before God. They are
presenting themselves before God.
Okay, and if you look at רשי Rashi at את מי הם
מעידים, et mi hem mei'idim, רשי Rashi says against who are they
testifying, כאילו הם מעידים בהקדוש ברוך הוא ke'ilu hem mei'idim baKadosh Baruch
Hu שמטריחין אותו להחזיר ממון לבעליו, shematrichin oto lehachazir mamon l'va'alav, because
if they testify falsely, God will have to, you know, administer the
justice and not the court. So your false testimony is, it can
impact, like you're making God have to work harder and God has
to go ahead and make this person get his money back. So
it's like you're testifying against God and you're perverting God's, you know,
the justice that's applying to God.
Okay. והיו הדיינים יודעים את מי הם דנים ולפני מי הם דנים
ומי עתיד ליפרע מהם, V'hayu hadayanim yodim et mi hem danim v'lifnei
mi hem danim umi atid lipara mehem, and
similarly the judges have to know who are they judging, you know,
in front of who are they judging and who will pay them
back. שנאמר Shenemar אלוקים ניצב בעדת אל, Elokim nitzav ba'adat E-l, God
stands in the congregation of God, which is understood that God is
present there among the judges. וכן ביהושפט הוא אומר v'chen biYehoshaphat hu
omer ויאמר אל השופטים, v'yomer el hashofetim, and he said to the
judges, וביהושפט v'biYehoshaphat he said to the judges, ראו מה אתם עושים
כי לא לאדם תשפטו כי להשם. re'u mah atem osim ki lo
l'adam tishpetu ki l'Hashem. See what you are doing, for you
are not judging humans, it's a judgment of God. You're instilling God's
justice, but also to some degree you're impacting God by perverting justice.
שמא יאמר דיין מה לי בצער זה, Shema yomar dayan mah li
betza'ar zeh, lest the judge says, why do I need this all
of this anguish? Like this is too much responsibility, I'm just checking
out. תלמוד לומר Talmud lomar עמכם בדבר משפט, imachem bidvar mishpat, that
God is with you in the matter of judgment. Meaning not just
saying it's too much responsibility but oh my God, if I get
something wrong, I'm all going to have to pay. I can't deal
with it, like I'll be terrified that I'm going to פוסק posek
incorrectly. No, God is with you. אין לו לדיין אלא מה שעיניו
רואות, Ein lo l'dayan ela mah she'einav ro'ot, that if you deal
with integrity, then you, nobody expects you to be a superhero and
you can only judge as much as best as you can assess
the situation. So as long as you do it with honesty and
integrity and with rigor and so on, then God is with you
and you do not have to fear for, you know, making mistakes.
Okay? And therefore not to withhold yourself. רב משה פיינשטיין Rav Moshe
Feinstein talks about that as פסק הלכה. psak halacha. If you go
through the process with integrity, whatever you come up with will be
legitimate הלכה. halacha. You know, that's like the idea of לא בשמים
היא, Lo bashamayim hi, not exactly this גמרא's Gemara point, but like
you can understand the trepidation of responsibility.
Okay. היכי דמי גמר דין. Heichi dami gmar din. Now back to
the earlier point that once there's גמר דין, gmar din, you know,
you cannot be בוצע. botzea. That's according to everybody. You know, there
were different opinions once they came in front of you, once you
know היכן הדין נוטה, heichan hadin noteh, at what stage maybe you
should not be בוצע, botzea, but it certainly is not allowed once
there's גמר דין. gmar din. So what's
גמר דין? gmar din? אמר רב יהודה אמר רב Amar Rav Yehuda
amar Rav איש פלוני אתה חייב איש פלוני אתה זכאי. ish ploni
atah chayav ish ploni atah zakai. When they say you're liable or
you're exempt, that is גמר דין. gmar din. Pretty clear that after
that, I mean I don't know who would be stupid enough to
agree to a פשרה psharah at that point. But anyway. אמר רב
הלכה כרבי יהושע בן קרחה. Amar Rav halacha k'Rabbi Yehoshua ben Korcha.
We rule like רבי יהושע בן קרחה Rabbi Yehoshua ben Korcha who's
who was the one who said it's a מצוה לבצוע mitzvah livtzoa
and called it משפט שלום. mishpat shalom. Okay, so איני, eini, is
this really true? ורב הונא תלמידיה דרב הוה, v'Rav Huna talmidei d'Rav
havah, Rav Huna was a student of Rav, so presumably followed the
ruling here of that we go like
רבי יהושע בן קרחה Rabbi Yehoshua ben Korcha and כי הוו אתו
לקמיה דרב הונא, ki havu atu l'kamei d'Rav Huna, and when litigants
came to Rav Huna, he would say to them, אי דינא בעיתו
אי פשרה בעיתו. ee dina beitu ee pshara beitu. What do you
want? Do you want me to deal with you to be a
normal case, you know, normal according to the law, justice, or do
you want פשרה psharah compromise? And according to רבי יהושע בן קרחה,
Rabbi Yehoshua ben Korcha, presumably it says מצוה לבצוע, mitzvah livtzoa, so
you should actually be encouraging them, right? You lay out all the
options or do you try to... Point them in one direction? So
the גמרא Gemara says no. מאי מצוה נמי דקאמר רבי יהושע בן
קרחה, mai mitzva nami dekamar Rebbe Yehoshua ben Korcha, top of ז'
עמוד א', zayin amud aleph, מצוה למימר להו אי דינא בעיתו אי
פשרה בעיתו. mitzva lemeimar lehu ee dina bayisu ee pshara bayisu. You,
it doesn't mean that you're supposed to encourage them specifically to pick
it, but you are supposed to lay it out as an equal,
as an equal offering. Okay, so you have the first opinions, you
know, that would have said like, once they come in front of
you, it's forbidden for you to go down that path. Once, or,
you know, a slightly lighter version of that, once you know where
it's heading, it's forbidden for you to go down that path. And
רבי יהושע בן קרחה Rebbe Yehoshua ben Korcha says no, even when
they come down to you, there's a value in being בוצע, botzeah,
but as opposed to saying you should push it and encourage it,
he's saying you should lay it out as an equal and an
equal possibility. All right.
So the גמרא Gemara says, היינו תנא קמא? hainu tanna kamma? But
wait, once you're just saying that you can offer it, how is
that different than the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma who says אסור לבצוע?
assur livtzoah? So the גמרא Gemara says no, איכא בינייהו מצוה, ika
beina'ihu mitzva, that this is exactly the difference that not the תנא
קמא Tanna Kamma that said אסור לבצוע. assur livtzoah. Obviously this is
different than אסור. assur. This is saying it's מותר, muttar, you can
lay it out. But how is this different than the תנא קמא
Tanna Kamma who said once it's נגמר הדין, nigmar hadin, you can't
be בוצע? botzeah? From that it sounds like beforehand, it's an option.
So if the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma was saying before גמר דין
gmar din it's an option, and רבי יהושע בן קרחה Rebbe Yehoshua
ben Korcha is saying it's an option, aren't they saying the same
thing? So the גמרא Gemara says no, איכא בינייהו מצוה. ika beina'ihu
mitzva. So no, the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma said it's not forbidden,
but he's not interested in you suggesting it. If they ask for
it, you can do it. Whereas רבי יהושע בן קרחה Rebbe Yehoshua
ben Korcha says no, you actually should suggest it. So the גמרא
Gemara stepped away from the idea possibility that you should actively promote
it, but we still have the פסק psak of רבי יהושע בן
קרחה Rebbe Yehoshua ben Korcha that says even when they come to
you, maybe even after you've heard them, maybe who knows, maybe even
after you know היכן הדין נוטה, heychan hadin noteh, but certainly anyway
at earlier stages, it's a מצוה mitzva to let them know that
this is an option. Whereas the other opinions are like no. At
a certain stage it's אסור, assur, once they come, once you know
היכן הדין נוטה, heychan hadin noteh, and maybe even at an earlier
stage even if it's not אסור assur you shouldn't be mentioning it.
If they suggest it, you can go down that path. Okay, so
now the גמרא Gemara says like this: So איכא בינייהו מצוה. ika
beina'ihu mitzva. רבי יהושע בן קרחה Rebbe Yehoshua ben Korcha סבר מצוה,
savar mitzva, תנא קמא Tanna Kamma סבר רשות. savar reshus. So the
גמרא Gemara says, היינו דרבי שמעון בן מנסיא? hainu de-Rabbi Shimon ben
Menasya? One minute, says the גמרא, Gemara, that if the תנא קמא
Tanna Kamma is saying that you know, if they raise it you
can go down that path, then and but only but not after
there's גמר דין, gmar din, isn't that what רבי יהושע בן קרחה
Rebbe Yehoshua ben Korcha said? He said that you know, once you
know where the דין din is נוטה noteh you can't go down
the path. So no, there's a difference. איכא בינייהו משתשמע דבריהם ואתה
יודע היכן הדין נוטה אי אתה רשאי לומר להם צאו ובצעו. ika
beina'ihu mishetishprei divreihem ve'atta yodea heychan hadin noteh i atta reshai lomar
lahem tze'u u-bitzu.
The question is that you know, that how at what point is
it no longer allowed to be saying it. For the תנא קמא,
Tanna Kamma, even if you know where it's going, you know, up
to the moment you say you give the פסק דין, psak din,
you can allow them to go ahead and do a פשרה. pshara.
According to רבי שמעון בן מנסיא Rebbe Shimon ben Menasya you're not
allowed to once you know היכן הדין נוטה. heychan hadin noteh. So
to review: you have the פסק psak of who was it? Of
רבי יהושע בן קרחה, Rebbe Yehoshua ben Korcha, מצוה לבצוע, mitzva livtzoah,
which means even after they come to you and even maybe well
into the whole judgment and who knows, you should be let them
know proactively let them know that this is an option. Maybe don't
דוקא davka encourage it, but proactively let them know that this is
an option. According to all the other opinions keep your mouth shut,
don't let them know about it, if they suggest it then there's
a debate. You know, there was the one opinion that said רבי
אליעזר בנו של רבי יוסי הגלילי Rebbe Eliezer beno shel Rebbe Yose
HaGlili that even if they suggest it you are not allowed to
go down that path once they come in front of you in
the court. You know, you've got the תנא Tanna you've got
רבי שמעון בן מנסיא, Rebbe Shimon ben Menasya, excuse me, who says
you can go down that path until you know היכן הדין נוטה,
heychan hadin noteh, and the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma that you can
go down that path until it is actually גמר דין. gmar din.
All right. Now, ופליגא דרבי תנחום בר חנילאי. u-pliga de-Rebbe Tanchum bar
Chanilai. This argues on רבי תנחום בר חנילאי, Rebbe Tanchum bar Chanilai,
דאמר רבי תנחום בר חנילאי, de'amar Rebbe Tanchum bar Chanilai, לא נאמר
מקרא זה אלא כנגד מעשה העגל. lo ne'emar mikra zeh ella keneged
ma'aseh ha'egel. This פסוק pasuk about בוצע ברך, botzeah berech, you know
the way we were using it for like about פשרה, pshara, he
says that was not said about פשרה, pshara, it was said about
the חטא העגל, cheit ha'egel, where אהרן Aharon made a compromise. Okay,
and so let's take a look. If you look at רש"י, Rashi,
last of the wide lines of רש"י Rashi at the top, אלא
כנגד מעשה העגל, ella keneged ma'aseh ha'egel, שעשה אהרן פשרה בינו לבין
עצמו והורה היתר לעצמו לעשות להם העגל. she'asa Aharon pshara beino levein
atzmo ve-horeh heter le'atzmo la'asot lahem ha'egel. He compromised with his own
conscience and integrity and came up with this you know with this
approach.
Okay, so שנאמר, shene'emar, as the פסוק pasuk says, וירא אהרן ויבן
מזבח לפניו, vaya'ar Aharon vayiven mizbeiach lefanav, מה ראה אהרן? mah ra'ah
Aharon? a altar? אמר רבי בנימין בר יפת, amar rabbi binyamin bar
yefet, אמר רבי אלעזר: amar rabbi elazar: ראה חור שזבוח לפניו. ra
chur she-zevuach lefanav. Brilliant read of the פסוק pasuk because משה moshe
says, הנה אהרן וחור עמכם. hineh aharon ve-chur imachem. אהרן aharon and
חור chur are here, but when משה moshe returns, אהרן aharon is
there, what happened to חור? chur? So the גמרא, gemara, the מדרש
midrash says, you know, they killed him. He tried to stop the
people and they killed him. So the גמרא'ס gemara's reading the פסוק:
pasuk: וירא אהרן ויבן, vayar aharon vayiven, he understood מזבוח
לפניו mi-zevuach lefanav from the one who had been slaughtered in his
presence. He understood that he could not stand up to them or
he was going to die. So he had to come up with
some type of a reasonable thing to maybe dissuade them, but not
to directly confront them. You know, that's always the question. It gets
back to the story before about יהודה, yehuda, about ראובן, reuven, what
ראובן reuven did to try to sell יוסף yosef about half measures,
you know, if you try to go the whole distance you're going
to get yourself killed and not accomplish anything. But the גמרא gemara
here is not having any of it. Okay, אמר... amar... so אמר
רבי אלעזר: amar rabbi elazar: ראה חור שזבוח לפניו, ra chur she-zevuach
lefanav, he saw חור chur that was slaughtered and אמר amar said:
אילו שמענא להו השתא עבדו לי כדעבדו בחור. ilu sham'inu lehu hashta
avidu li kedavdu ve-chur. If I don't listen to them and build
the עגל, egel, they'll do to me like they did to חור
chur now. That could just be self-preservation, I don't want to get
killed, you know, but the גמרא gemara is making it a little
bit more than just self-preservation. ומקיים בי אם יהרג במקדש ה' כהן
ונביא, u'mkayem bi im yehareg be-Mikdash Hashem kohen ve-navi, that that פסוק
pasuk which hasn't been said yet, you know, but that's like oh
my god, the imagine the blasphemy, the tragedy that slaughtered a כהן
kohen and a נביא navi in the מקדש, mikdash, I'll be the
כהן kohen and נביא. navi. There wasn't a מקדש mikdash yet, but
okay. ולא הוי להו תקנתא לעולם. v'lo havi lehu takana le-olam. And
then, you know, one thing they killed חור, chur, but if they
kill me then it'll be so horrific that they'll never be forgiven.
So מוטב דנעבדו לעגל, mutav de-avidu le-egel, it's better that they should
do the עגל. egel. אפשר הוי להו תקנתא בתשובה. efshar havi lehu
takana be-teshuva. I'll make them the עגל egel and maybe and then
we can do תשובה. teshuva. It's עבודה זרה avoda zara but it's
not this thing that is so horrific. It's interesting. That would be
more horrific than עבודה זרה. avoda zara. It's also more horrific that
it's אהרן aharon and it's חור, chur, anyway. Okay, so it's interesting,
now maybe that was his own compromise, right? Maybe that was his
own מורה היתר, moreh heter, maybe he really was motivated by self-preservation,
but he was telling himself that he was doing it in order
to, you know, to save them from an even more grievous sin.
והני תנאי פוטר מים ראשית מדון מדדשי בה, ve-hani tana'ei poter mayim
reshith madon medarshi bei, and the other תנאים tanna'im that say that
you don't read this פסוק pasuk of פוטר מים ראשית מדון poter
mayim reshith madon that at a certain stage you're allowed to exempt
yourself, at a later stage you're not allowed to walk off, what
do they do with the פסוק? pasuk? So כרב המנונא, ke-Rav Hamnuna,
like רב המנונא, Rav Hamnuna, דאמר רב המנונא: d'amar Rav Hamnuna: אין
תחלת דינו של אדם נידון אלא על דברי תורה. ein chilat dino
shel adam nidon ela al divrei Torah. A person is first judged
in terms of, you know, his תורה. Torah. If
he was מבטל mevatel from תורה. Torah. שנאמר she-ne'emar as the פסוק
pasuk says, פוטר מים ראשית מדון. poter mayim reshith madon. If you
exempt yourself from מים, mayim, תורה Torah is compared to water, הוי
כל צמא לכו למים, hoi kol tzame lechu la-mayim, that is the
first that thing you will be judged on. אמר רב הונא: amar
Rav Huna: האי תיגרא דמייא לצינורא דבידקא דמיא. hai tigra de-maya le-tzinora
de-bidka damya. So this, you know,
excuse me, I think I read that wrong. האי בידקא, hai bidka,
one is to מאיא, maya, one is דמיא. damya. So האי תיגרא
דמיא, hai tigra damya, so a fight, what is it comparable to?
לצינורא דבידקא דמייא, le-tzinora de-bidka de-maya, like a hose that has, you
know, that has a crack in the hose. כיוון דרוח רוח, kivan
de-ravach ravach, that you know, once it gets wide it gets wide.
If you have a crack in the hose it'll just expand and
expand. So similarly, if you have a fight you need to try
to heal it right away or just it's going to get deeper
and deeper.
אביי קשישא אמר: abaye keshisha amar: דמיא לגודא דגמלא. damya le-guda de-gamla.
It's similar to a like a
board
of a bridge. כיוון דקם קם, kivan de-kam kam, that once it's
like been, you know, like established, stable, then it's going to be
firm. So you know, once a fight gets deep in, good luck
trying to, you know, to get people to reconcile. Okay. So now
the גמרא gemara continues, it's got these ראשי תיבות rashei teivot as
just a way of remembering it from an oral tradition. ההוא דהוה
קאמר, hahu de-hava ka-amar, there was a person who used to say,
ואזיל, ve-azil, he was going and he was saying: טוביה דשמע ואדיש,
tuvya de-shama ve-adish, it is good to somebody who hears like insults
and bad things being said to him and he basically like, you
know, ignores it or remains silent. חפויה בי שתי מאה. chafua bei
shtei me'ah. You know, a hundred misfortunes, bad things will not happen
to him as a result. Just let it all wash off of
you. Easier said than done. אמר ליה שמואל לרב יהודה, amar leh
Shmuel le-Rav Yehuda, so שמואל Shmuel said to רב יהודה, Rav Yehuda,
קרא כתיב, kra ketiv, it's a פסוק: pasuk: פוטר מים ראשית מדון.
poter mayim reshith madon. The one who releases water, it's the first
of מדון, madon, ריש מאה דיני. reish me'ah dinei. So reading מדון
madon as the beginning of a hundred litigations, a hundred judgments. So
if you release strife, the beginning of strife, you know, that's what
the simple sense means, is that, you know, brings out a hundred
judgments. So if you just let it go then you free yourself
from all of those bad things. רש"י rashi also points out that
the word מדון madon in גימטריה gematria is a hundred, it's also
מאה דיני. me'ah dinei. הוא דהוה קאמר ואזל Hu d'hava qamer v'azal
somebody was going and
saying אטרתי תלת
גן ולא מקטל atarti t'las gan v'lo miqtal that and he was
saying that that
like
somebody is not killed you know by God for two or three
sets meaning as רש״י Rashi says you know somebody does an עבירה
aveira two times three times nothing's happened to me you know you
think okay that's it like you're going to get away with it
God's going to God won't punish you or something like that. So
he was saying you know two or three times it won't happen
but eventually you'll get your judgment.
So אמר ליה שמואל לרב יהודה Amar lei Shmuel l'Rav Yehuda so
שמואל Shmuel said to רב יהודה Rav Yehuda קרא כתיב kra ksiv
it's in a פסוק pasuk כה אמר ה׳ על שלשה פשעי אדום
ועל ארבעה לא אשיבנו Ko amar Hashem al shlosha pish'ei Edom v'al
arba lo ashivenu on three and in four of the sins ישראל
Yisrael excuse me on four I will not you know pay them
back but more than that you know once it gets to be
enough they'll get their payment back. So it's interesting obviously we're starting
this discussion because of פוטר מים poter mayim but we're trying to
find ways in which like common aphorisms are already in the פסוקים.
psukim. ההוא דהוה קאמר ואזל Ahu d'hava ka'amar v'azal somebody who was
going and saying שב בירי לשלמנא וחדא לעביד ביש shav biri l'shamana
v'chada l'avid bish that
that there can be seven pits for somebody who is a man
of you know somebody who's like a good person a man of
peace and he'll avoid all of the traps but for a bad
person they'll fall into just one pit. You know if only life
worked that way. אמר ליה שמואל לרב יהודה Amar lei Shmuel l'Rav
Yehuda so שמואל Shmuel said to רב יהודה Rav Yehuda קרא כתיב
kra ksiv it's a פסוק pasuk כי שבע יפול צדיק
וקם ki sheva yipol tzadik v'kam that as the righteous will fall
seven times and get up so even if there are things that
are made there to make him stumble in the end he will
survive them and in the פסוק pasuk we and the גמרא Gemara
we have says ורשעים יפלו באחת v'rasha'im yiplu b'echat you know and
and a wicked person will fall in one but that's not actually
the פסוק. pasuk. And the פסוק pasuk you see it says in
the side ורשעים יכשלו ברעה. v'rasha'im yikashlu b'ra'a.
All right but anyway so but the wicked will stumble so even
a small thing somebody who's wicked will not recover. Again if only
the world worked that way. Okay. ההוא דהוה קאמר ואזל Ahu d'hava
ka'amar v'azal somebody who's going and saying דאזיל מבי דינא שקיל גלימא
ליזמור זמר וליזיל. d'azil mi'bei dina shakal glima lizmor zemar v'leizel.
That you know somebody goes from the court and his his garment
was taken from him you know he should be sing a song
and going happy on his way. באורחא וליזיל באורחא b'orcha v'leizel b'orcha
because because because ultimately he's now no longer holding onto stolen goods.
It's like the גמרא Gemara before about צדקה tzedaka you let him
to to be righteous. So אמר ליה שמואל לרב יהודה amar lei
Shmuel l'Rav Yehuda שמואל Shmuel said to רב יהודה Rav Yehuda קרא
כתיב kra ksiv it's a פסוק pasuk וגם כל העם הזה על
מקומו יבא בשלום v'gam kol ha'am hazeh al mekomo yavo v'shalom this
entire people will go to peace if you have good judgment even
the ones that are found guilty it'll be peace for everyone. ההוא
דהוה קאמר ואזל Ahu d'hava ka'amar v'azal somebody who's going and saying
היי נימא ודיקלא שפיל. hai nema v'dikla shapil. So if like
if a somebody is carrying a woman is carrying like a basket
on her head if she's dozing off ודיקלא שפיל v'dikla shapil the
basket will fall down. Okay like if you know if you're somebody
is nodding off like what is it lazy hands no that's idle
hands is the devil's hands but okay inattention will lead to bad
things happening. אמר ליה שמואל לרב יהודה Amar lei Shmuel l'Rav Yehuda
so שמואל Shmuel said to רב יהודה Rav Yehuda ההוא קרא כתיב
hahu kra ksiv it's a פסוק pasuk בעצלתיים ימך המקרה ba'atzaltaim yemach
hamikre that with you know in by laziness the the rafters will
will warp will warp will sink in. Okay. ההוא דהוה קאמר ואזל
Ahu d'hava ka'amar v'azal somebody who's going and saying גברא דרחיצנא עליה
אדיי לגזיזיה gavra d'rachitzna alei adyei ligzizei that the person that I
you know that I that I was relied upon lifted his fist
against me וקם v'kam and you know and got up. So you
know so he rose up against me. So I was betrayed. So
אמר ליה שמואל לרב יהודה amar lei Shmuel l'Rav Yehuda קרא כתיב
kra ksiv it's a פסוק pasuk וגם כי איש שלומי אשר בטחתי
בו v'gam ki ish shlomi asher batachti bo the person of my
you know of my faith that I had put my confidence in
you know that person basically
has the end of the פסוק pasuk is ate my bread and
lifted up you know lifted his foot against me. So all right
so people sometimes you know you trust somebody and they will betray
your trust. I'm not exactly sure what the point of that aphorism
is. ההוא דהוה קאמר ואזל Ahu d'hava ka'amar v'azal somebody who's going
and saying כי רחמתין הוי עזיזא אפותיא דספסירא שכיבינא ki richamtin hava
aziza apusia d'safsira shachivin when our כי רחמתין הוי עזיזא ki richamtin
hava aziza when our love was strong we would be able to
sleep on a bed like by like on the edge of a
sword. We could have you know when when in the good old
days when we were just married and we were you know we
lived in this tiny little hovel and everything was everything was amazing.
Okay the you know could have been very really living in straits
but our love kept us going. השתא דלא עזיזא רחמתין Hashta d'lo
aziza richimtan now that our love is not strong פורייא בר שיתין
גרמי puraya bar shitin garmi even a bed of sixty אמות amot
לא סגי לן lo sagi lan you know we have this nice
luxurious house and we can't stand each other and it just sings
our misery. So so it really is the love that makes the
difference not the you know not the physical and the material issues.
אמר רב הונא amar Rav Huna קראי כתיב krai ksiv it's a
פסוק pasuk מעיקרא כתיב ונועדתי לך שם ודברתי אתך מעל הכפורת meikar
ksiv v'no'adti lecha sham v'dibarti itcha me'al hakaporet originally God said I
will speak to you from above the ark meaning that the שכינה
Shechina came down and the ark was ten טפחים tefachim off of
the ground. Down and was right there with us, like, right in
the ten טפחים *tefachim* right before the space that was for the
human being, God's presence
was confined, you know, right in that little space. Okay, that's what
it originally was. ותניא *Vtanya*, ארון תשעה וכפורת טפח הרי כאן עשרה
*Aron tisha vekapporet tefach harei kan asara*. The ארון *Aron* was nine
טפחים *tefachim* and the כפורת *kapporet* a טפח *tefach*. That's עשרה טפחים
*asara tefachim*. God was right there within ten טפחים *tefachim* of the
ground. So close to us. וכתיב *Uksiv*, but then later it says
והבית אשר בנה שלמה לה' שישים אמה ארכו *Vehabayit asher bana Shlomo
l'Hashem shishim ama orko*. The בית המקדש *Beis Hamikdash* that שלמה *Shlomo*
built, sixty אמות *amos* wide, ועשרים רחבו ושלושים אמה קומתו *ve'esrim rochvo
ushloshim ama komato*, thirty אמות *amos* tall. You have this huge thirty
אמות *amos*. ולבסוף כתיב *Ulevasof ksiv*, and then when we sinned, it
says כה אמר ה' השמים כסאי והארץ הדום רגלי אי זה בית
אשר תבנו לי *Ko amar Hashem hashamayim kisi veha'aretz hadom raglai ei
zeh bayit asher tivnu li*. You know, what house will you make
for me? Meaning, I'm leaving this house, I can't dwell with you
anymore. So God not only couldn't be squeezed down to the ten
אמות *amos*, ten טפחים *tefachim*, He couldn't even be in a house
that had thirty אמה *ama* high. He had to leave the whole
house. Okay, מאי משמע דהאי לא תגורו *Mai mashma dehai lo taguru*?
Now, just wrapping up, where do you get this idea that לא
תגורו *lo taguru* לישנא דכנושי הוא *lishna d'kinushei hu*? When it says
you can't hold your words back if you see that the judgment
belong, you know, like you see that something needs to be said
in the court, and the גמרא *Gemara* said even if you're a
student, don't hold your words back. Where do you see that's the
word לא תגורו *lo taguru*? אמר רב נחמן אמר קרא *Amar Rav
Nachman amar kra*, the פסוק *pasuk* says ויין לא תשתה ולא תאגור
*Veyayin lo tishteh velo te'egor*. Wine you won't drink and you won't
gather in. So it means to gather in. רב אחא בר יעקב
אמר מהכא *Rav Acha bar Yaakov amar meihacha*, תכין בקיץ לחמה *Tachin
bakayitz lachma*. It prepares in, this is about like the industrious ant,
prepares in the summer its bread, אגרה בקציר מאכלה *agra bakkatzir ma'achala*,
gathers up in the harvest season its food. רב אחא בריה דרב
איקא אמר מהכא *Rav Acha brei deRav Ika amar meihacha*, אוגר בקיץ
בן משכיל *Oger bakayitz ben maskil*. That in the summer a wise
son will gather. So אוגר *oger* means to gather. Okay, we will
end here.